Jayden, are you there?
Hello.
Could you make the classroom a class?
Oh, yes.
Yes.
Please.
Okay, try now.
All right.
First we'll share that.
And then we'll share the Captiva whiteboard.
There we go.
All right, can you see everything Jayden?
Jaden, can you see everything?
I can see the screen share.
Can you write on the whiteboard?
Yeah, sure.
We haven't been testing but I...
Yeah, I can see that too.
All right, cool.
Great.
All right, so welcome back.
This is our last week together, except if you're coming next week for the final.
If you're not coming to the classroom, then you are going to be going to proctoring or whatever,
so make sure you're registered.
There were a few people who were not registered as of this afternoon when I checked.
It's important.
I'm not going to start.
I already sent an email last night, so I'm not going to send anymore.
So just please register.
Everybody needs to register unless you're in Section 901.
If you're in Section 901, then you are not flex.
You're not one of the flex students, so you have to come to the classroom for the exam.
If you're in Section 941, you must register, so make sure you do that.
Another announcement.
I need to move office hours tomorrow.
Nobody's been coming to office hours, but I'm still available if you need me.
But I have to move it to Thursday this week.
So Thursday, I sent this out by email and it's posted on D2L.
Thursday at 8.30 until 9.15.
So reach out if you need anything.
I will also do office hours before the exam on Tuesday next week.
So I'll be here in the classroom at usual time, like four 50.
Definitely sent me a message on a discord cause I don't rush if I don't think
anybody's coming and so far almost nobody's been coming.
So, um, today somebody was using the room and I went out and got coffee, so,
you know, it's fine, but definitely let me know if you are coming,
because then that way I will make sure to give you the time that you deserve.
And also if for some reason we don't end up with enough time,
we can figure out an alternate time, right?
so stay in touch if you want that. So the other thing is there's still the extra
credit there's the quiz that I added for the Computer Science Program assessment
you should do that and then tonight because I am required to give you extra
time in the classroom to do your course evaluation. So course evaluations are still open. So what we
will do is we'll take a longer break at break time. And I think what I'm going to do is I'm
going to cover some new material tonight. This is all bonus material. I just want to talk about it
because it's very interesting from a computing standpoint. And as master's programming students
like this is computer science students who are studying programming.
I think this is kind of some good stuff to know about.
So I'm going to cover that first.
Then we're going to do some review at the second half, right?
So what we'll do is we'll do that first, and then we'll take our longer break,
which will be about 25 minutes.
So, or no, yeah, 25 minutes.
We'll take a longer break.
So you'll have a normal 15-minute break plus an extra 10 minutes to do your evaluation.
You can do it at your own time.
so on the evaluations um i don't get to see what you write until after i turn in grades they don't
even send them out until after grades are completely done for the quarter so i strongly
encourage you to fill out um your evaluation and add comments um you know i do get to read the
written comments and one quarter a student wrote some things that made it very easy for me to
figure out who she was. She wasn't happy. These things happen. So just be aware that I do get to
read what you write. So if you write something and I can identify who it is, then I know who it is.
And I'm not saying like, I mean, I'll never see you again, probably, but just be aware of that.
Right. So so that's that's kind of the lay of the land. If you're a 941 and you're already
registered the earliest time for your final exam would be this coming Thursday
and then for 941 you can go all the way until night like it ends at 9 p.m. on
Tuesday so you can take your exam your proctoring sorry on Thursday if you're
in section again I know like you just come here on Tuesday and then so so the
exam is all set up with proctoring people so everything should don't send
me questions about like I forgot my ID like I don't run I don't if you please
bring your ID to the classroom if you're taking me but I don't run proctoring
like I don't have anything to I give them the exams I uploaded and then I'm
done and then they administer and then they send it back to me that's it and
then they give me the original is back later so that's it so that's the lay of
land for the next week. Alright, so a week from today the final will be over, and then you'll all
be done. But do your extra credit now if you want to do it. Because don't come to me like, you know,
Tuesday or Monday like, oh, I bombed the exam and I need all the extra credit I can get, and I didn't
do it. Well, I'm not gonna mess it around, like just do it, okay? Like just do it now. So, alright,
All right. So here we are at Week 10. So when we get back from the break, we'll cover the quiz, and we'll cover the study guide questions for JavaScript, and we'll also cover some other review stuff. But let's start with Java concurrency.
So I have a lot of experience with the JVM.
I was a Java programmer for at least 15 years professionally.
I say at least because somewhere in there, there was a crossover into Scala,
and I was still doing both languages for a while.
And I also, everything that we do in Scala is built on the JVM,
so that knowledge carries with me.
All right, so when we talk about concurrency, we're talking about concurrent execution.
So we're going to talk about threads and share immutable state.
We're going to identify race conditions and data races.
We'll talk about synchronization mechanisms, locks, synchronized blocks and atomic operations
and then we'll describe higher-level concurrency abstractions in Java and we'll compare them
compare concurrency approaches across languages.
So this is just a little bit of survey of how we,
as computer science people, deal with executing
on modern hardware.
Our modern hardware can support multiple threads
executing in parallel.
And so how do we have a program share
memory across those threads?
So why do we need concurrent programs?
So we have multiple cores.
If we just had sequential programs, we would be wasting resources.
Those other cores would sit idle.
Now back in the early days of computing, you only had single cores, right?
So, you know, languages like C didn't really natively support dealing with multiple threads.
Many problems that we have on our modern programming or modern computing world, or modern world,
using the latest technology, are naturally concurrent.
So web servers, GUIs, simulations, things are happening and things have to happen in parallel.
So there's a difference between concurrency and parallelism.
So concurrency is dealing with multiple things at once, so that's structure.
And parallelism is doing multiple things at once, execution.
So structure and execution.
So those are the two kind of things to keep in mind.
So concurrency, dealing with multiple things at once, is a language design problem.
How do we express and control it?
So Java was one of the first mainstream languages that was built with support for threads built
in.
So I remember when this came out, it was a big deal.
So what is a thread?
So a thread is a lightweight unit of execution.
So in this code here we have an example program, hello, thread.
We have a main program.
It creates a new thread, and you see it's using a lambda expression.
So the interface, you have to pass something to thread that implements runnable.
I think it could also do callable now, I don't know.
but in the old days it was all runnable, right?
And this is really an implementation of the run method.
So it would look like the actual method on the interface
is public void run, and there's no parameters.
And run, when you call it, your thread calls it,
and it needs to run and do whatever it's supposed to do.
So in this case, it's going to print out hello from thread
and print out the name, and that's all it's going to do.
And then it's going to, down here after we've
constructed the thread we say start,
And then we say hello from main.
This is hello from thread.
This is hello from main.
So we might get these two pieces of output out of order.
This may be executing this line and printing out
before that line is printed out.
So that's just a simple example.
So the order of the output, we say that's non-deterministic.
because the machine that's running it is going to,
because of entropy on the machine,
it's going to run each thread
when it makes sense in that environment
at that time while it's running.
So if you run it again, you might get a different order.
So then we come into this problem, we have this problem here.
What happens when two threads modify the same variable?
So if I have that code that has,
in this case, we're starting a new thread,
we're starting another new thread and each of
these threads is touching this memory, right?
Notice we're in our threads.
This one, we have a for loop that goes from 0 to 100,000 and
also in this one, we have a for loop that goes from 0 to 100,000.
So we would expect 200,000 would be the value for count and
we're only gonna end up with S.
Okay, so why is that?
So this is called a race condition.
The result is different every time.
Let's talk about Y-headits.
So the way our computers work, we have, hopefully you know from systems,
We have memory.
We have RAM.
This is where our heap is, this is where our stack is,
that's all in our RAM.
And we have processors.
So here's a processor.
And this is called a cache.
So if we didn't have a cache, every time we did something with memory, and that memory
It can be registers, it can be RAM.
We also have registers, I guess I'll put that here, register.
And I'm using memory loosely, because usually when
we talk about memory on a computer,
we say they have so many gigabytes of RAM or whatever.
But I'm just saying this is weird.
I don't remember where the registers live, actually.
Do they live on the processor?
I can't remember.
Who remembers?
I don't remember.
I believe that they live on the process.
I think you're right.
I think they live on the process.
See, I don't think at this level very often, right?
I don't have to think at this level very often.
I'm putting that over here because I think where I'm going with this is Java,
when it deals with stuff in the registers.
There are rules and those rules apply here,
so I'm going to just revise my picture.
I'm just gonna just leave this as memory. I think I think you're right there, Dylan. I think the
registers are over here.
Alright. So what happens? Well if we didn't have this cache, we would be going to memory every time.
And we would have to go across the bus on the motherboard. Right? And this is slow.
Slower than it would be if we had the data
So what they do is they have a processor cache.
And that's why I drew it attached to the processor.
So what happened here is that, because we're not using some,
we'll get to later in this lecture how Java deals with this stuff.
But what happened here is that when we have a thread executing,
It needs to get data so the JVM will actually probably ask the operating system.
It will get the data and then it will put it in the processor cache.
And it's a copy.
And while the program is executing, it will update this copy.
And eventually it will push that back to main memory.
But that's a lot slower for that to happen.
Meanwhile, if the thread gets suspended
or another thread comes in
and starts using that same location in memory
it's going to get a different copy, an older copy,
a stale copy of the data, right?
So that's what this is.
So when Java came out, we were starting
to have processors that had multiple,
support for multiple threads.
And so when Java came out, they designed it in such a way
so that there are certain rules about accessing the .
So what happened here in this code?
We got this different result than we expected.
It's because we basically ended up writing old data.
So we would update.
Then another thread would kick in and update.
And we would think that we had updated that counter.
But then the JVM and the OS would push that back
domain memory. That older value from the other thread. Okay, so that's why you get this.
So why is count plus plus broken? Well, it's not a single operation. It's three. So both threads
have to read 42. Say we're at 42. Both threads read 42. Both write 43 in one increments lost.
And you have a data race. So there's unsynchronized access to shared mutable state or at least one
and access these array.
So that can happen if they're sharing the memory
in the processor cache.
So the interleaving depends on the os thread scheduler,
and this is going to be non-terminative.
The compiler, and furthermore we'll see later on,
the compiler can actually reorder operations
on you to make it more efficient.
So what can we do to solve this?
So if we want to use locks, you may have studied mutexes somewhere.
I first learned about mutexes in operating systems class.
In fact, it was when Java was coming out that my professor said,
we're all gonna use Java and we're gonna use it to learn operating systems.
We're mostly simulating what happens in operating systems.
But threads were a nice way to simulate processes in operating systems.
So what we're doing here is when we do this,
We have this object block and we're synchronizing on it.
And that means everything in this block is critical region,
that's what it's saying.
And that critical region, when we're incrementing this,
we are actually forced to write the result all the way out to main memory
before the synchronized block ends.
And so no other piece of code that's synchronizing on the same lock object
can see any data from there until we have released it
and the JVM has written update out.
So in this case, this will be correct every time.
So Java also lets you synchronize entire methods,
You may have seen synchronize in your life in Java somewhere,
but if you do synchronize on a method,
that means it's locking on this,
if it's a static method, it's locking on class.
Only one thread connects to any synchronize method on that object at the time.
Is that different from there?
I was there.
Sorry.
So is this enough?
What can go wrong?
What happens when two threads each wait for the other's lock?
So here we have lock A and lock B.
So first, in this thread we're going to synchronize on lock A, and
then we're gonna synchronize on lock B, and then we're gonna print out T1.
That's the name of that thread.
In this other thread, we're going to synchronize first on lock B,
and then we're going to synchronize on lock A, and then we're going to print out T2.
What happens if I try to run this code?
Does anybody have any clue?
I'm just wondering how much Java and how much concurrency you've dealt with.
Does it actually do anything?
I mean, it does something, but do you actually get any output?
I would say no because the name of the class is deadlock.
Bingo.
OK.
Well, that's not the reason, but that's the clue, right?
Yeah.
So what's a deadlock?
Do you know?
All right.
A deadlock is when you have two locks in play, or more, and the order of locking is not the
same.
And so T1 is going to hold lock A, and it's waiting for lock B. And if T2 holds lock
lock B and is waiting for lock A then no one's ever going to yield and they're just going
to sit there and stare at each other like they're arguing, they call that a standoff
or something.
So deadlock, both threads freeze forever.
Now actually, that code might actually run if thread one starts and runs and releases
all locks before thread two even starts to try.
So it's possible that it will run, but it's highly likely that it won't.
or it's non-deterministic.
So Java doesn't actually prevent deadlocks.
It's the programmer's responsibility.
So deadlocks, if you ever are a Java programmer,
you're working with a JVM in a production environment,
and you see a deadlock,
then you have a big bug in your code.
Like you can actually, I think it's,
I forget if it's jstack,
there's some command you can type to get a thread dump,
which will print out like what threads are,
like what locks they're waiting on.
And actually it won't be able to analyze to see if you actually
have a deadlock.
Before they had JSTAC, we all had to send a signal.
So you can use the kill command in Linux to send a signal.
And I still do the old school kill dash three, which
doesn't actually kill the process.
It sends a signal to the process.
The OS sends the signal and then it
tells it to do something.
And essentially what the JVM will do
is dump all the threads so you can analyze.
So if we have shared mutable state and multiple threads,
we have pain.
This is hard to get right.
It's hard to test, and it's hard to debug.
So the question is, can language design help us?
I might actually have to leave this lecture
at the beginning of the class,
because this motivates all functional programming.
We'll see what I'm about to say.
So recall that Rust, we saw this in Rust.
It prevents data races at compile time by this thing called aliasing XOR mutability.
Basically what Rust is doing is it has this very strong sense of ownership,
who owns the memory, right?
And the compiler enforces that.
So that's how Rust prevents data races.
In functional programming, we avoid the problem by using immutable data, right?
So if the data is immutable, we can't change the memory.
We've eliminated the problem.
This problem here, everybody has their own copy of data.
Or if they are sharing data, it's read-only.
So if it's read-only, there's none of this problem.
So for simple operations, Java actually
has these lock-free atomic classes.
I don't know if you've ever seen these like atomic integer.
But if you have, this will also work without using synchronization.
And actually, the motivation for this is that it's slightly faster than using synchronization.
Synchronization, the problem with using synchronized in Java is it can be very slow.
There was a time, though, in Java where this didn't even exist yet,
and the only way to get any sort of thread safety was volatile and synchronized.
And actually, the early version of Java, volatile was broken.
We'll cover volatile a little bit later, but it was broken.
they had to fix it later. So atomic integer uses hardware level compare and swap operations.
So this is actually an operation at the hardware level. There's an instruction in the JVM instruction
set that makes it so that we can use that instruction, compare and swap, we'll make
it so that we don't actually have to use a lock.
Okay, so what about visibility between threads?
So if we have this main program here,
and we have a new thread that is,
oh, it says while running, it will just spin.
And eventually, if that ever exits, it will print stop.
And out here, I'm changing my running to false.
I might never actually see that.
So what could happen there is without volatile, the JVM, like cache running in a register,
you know, that's a strong indicator that registers around a processor.
The thread never sees the other names.
So volatile forces reads and writes to go through main memory.
an volatile will guarantee visibility but not atomicity of compound operations.
So, CPUs are allowed, I said this earlier, to reorder instructions and cache memory for
performance reasons.
And there are certain rules they have to follow, the compiler has to follow.
The compiler can reorder and the CPUs can reorder.
Without these rules, the threads might see stale or inconsistent data.
So this volatile and synchronized and the compare and swap stuff,
they all involve something called a happens before relationship.
So that lock object we had by the way is also sometimes,
whenever we do synchronize, we use a monitor.
That's another primitive for concurrency control.
I didn't realize my slides talk about monitor and we never define monitor.
So sorry about that, but it's the same idea as a lock.
So unlock on a monitor or a locked object.
That's the synchronized block ending, right?
That's where the brace was in your source code.
The closed brace, unlock on a monitor happens before a subsequent lock on that monitor.
So, no other thread can go in there.
if another thread is in that critical region inside the braces in a
synchronized block, no other thread can get in there. If I'm writing to a
volatile field, that write happens before a subsequent read. So if I have
another thread that comes along and tries to read from that volatile field,
it will be blocked because, or yeah, if I have a write going on somewhere else in
another thread, it will not be able to read until that write has occurred.
If I call thread dot start, that happens before any action in the started thread.
And all actions in the thread have to happen before thread dot join returns.
So thread dot join is when you have multiple threads and
you're trying to like bring them all back together,
like you're trying to wait until they end.
And I often put volatile in my code and my coworkers don't like it.
And then I tell them why.
And then they're like, oh, I didn't know that.
Because nobody thinks about that, about the JBL.
So without happens before, you have no guarantee about what one thread
sees from another thread.
This is something that comes from the specification of the language.
So the Java language specification actually defines this happens before relationship.
You can actually Google it, happens before Java language specification, and you'll find
it.
It constrains what the JVM and the CPU can optimize.
Okay, so thread pools.
So in our earlier examples we were actually constructing our own threads, right?
Don't do that.
So we learned that it's better to use the thread pool.
So this thing that we had before, the examples we had before were thread per task.
So there's a task, we create a thread for it, and then it has that thread.
If you use a thread pool, then you're limiting yourself to a certain number of threads.
So here I'm saying I want this is Java, so in Java,
I'm saying new fixed thread pool four.
I want four threads in my thread pool.
And then I can add work to...
I can add work to the pool.
So that's how this works.
This is a little bit beyond.
I have done this stuff before
but they've changed some of the ways that it works
so that I don't do this every day anymore.
I work in other frameworks that do all the concurrency
actually abstracted away from me.
but the good thing is I have the experience to actually know how this stuff works so
that when I look at that other code, I can make sense of it.
All right, so here in this code,
so does anybody know what a future is?
Anybody seen a future yet in their time?
It's a unit of computation,
so you have some computation that you're going to do.
And the future can either be in two states, uncompleted or completed.
So when the future is uncompleted, the computation is still going.
When the future is completed, then it has been resolved.
So what this is doing is it's saying I'm going to...
Here I have pool.submiss.
So this is my runnable.
It's a lambda, right?
That's why I like when I look at this.
And it looks very different than I used to say.
New runnable, you had to type it all the time.
So it was, what was that?
We covered that last week.
An anonymous class, right?
If you say new runnable here, then that's an anonymous class.
OK, so it ends up sleeping for 100 milliseconds
and you're turning end by end.
And when you say pool.submit, you get a future back.
So what you're doing is you're saying to the thread pool,
I am submitting work to you.
And the thread pool gives you a future,
and it will not report that future is completed
until it's done doing the work.
So we're saving those off in a list, in this array list,
and then later on we're iterating over the futures,
and we're getting the results.
And these, if you call get,
you're trying to get the result of the computation,
so the result of the computation is integer,
because it's the future of integers.
And this get call will block,
meaning like it won't return until the computation is done.
Then of course, you have to shut down the pool.
All right, so executor service is an interface in Java
and that's for managing a pool of reusable threads.
I remember the days in Java
when I worked at the SIBO down the street
where we wrote our own thread pool
because Java didn't have this executor service stuff yet.
It didn't come out until, I forget,
I think it was Java 1.5, I can't remember.
So that was around 2005-ish when it came, maybe 2008,
but I think it was 2005.
So future, of course, has a type parameter, right?
So we talked about that.
So future t is a handle to a result that will be available
later, and so we're abstracting orbit type t.
Here we're using integer as our fixed type in that example.
there are all kinds of variations.
There's completable future,
so with a completable future you can chain asynchronous operations.
This gives you a more functional style.
This is way beyond anything I've ever done with Java because I do this in
type level Scala this type of thing.
We don't actually use futures in Scala.
Well, you can use futures in Scala.
They do have that actually,
but I have moved into type level world,
where all of that stuff is completely abstracted out.
We just say F. It's not even a future anymore.
It's just an abstract effect.
We abstract it out the future part.
We like abstraction.
More and more abstraction.
So this here, we'll take, and you have a future here
that will produce hello, and then it will apply world.
it'll concatenate hello and world,
and then it will apply the string two uppercase functions,
that's a static function, and then it will accept,
by accept means it'll print, it'll call this,
this is currying actually what we see here,
it's calling printLine on that result,
and then join is a wait for completion,
so you'll end up with hello world here.
Oh yeah, because we call it two uppercase,
we end up with hello world.
But it will do these like you're composing these asynchronous operations.
Each of these are separate asynchronous operations.
So this is very much like map and flat map on future in Scala.
So Scala does have a future, and we have map and flat map on our futures as well.
With map and flat map on futures, of course, you have to wait for the initial future to complete the computation
before you can execute the function that you're passing to the map or the flat map function.
So we don't have any explicit threads here.
There are no locks.
The framework is handling all the scheduling.
So we've started to move into that world,
and that was the motivation, I think,
for some of the work that's been done in Type-Level Scala.
And Zio is the other big framework they use in Scala.
That's all just a more pure, functional program.
So Java provides thread-safe collection for implementations.
So this, yeah, this is unsafe.
So HashMap is not going to be thread-safe.
So if I have two threads modifying a HashMap, I might see a concurrent modification exception.
I don't know if anybody's ever seen that, but if you have, that's why.
Or you might silently corrupt your HashMap.
So that's no good either.
If you use a concurrent HashMap, I think underneath the covers,
this one's gonna use a compare and swap operation on the hardware level.
So this is, if you have two threads modifying this,
you end up with correct behavior, there are no locks needed by the caller.
So concurrent HashMap uses fine-grain locking internally,
it's much better than wrapping everything in synchronized,
which is a lot slower as I say.
collections dot synchronized map exists.
That was the old way before concurrent hash map came out,
so they added to Java by adding to the library.
So that will lock the whole map and that's a lot slower.
I think with concurrent hash map,
you might be able to do reads
if a write is happening at the same time
of touching another area, I don't know for sure.
It certainly is feasibility.
So a classic concurrency pattern using blocking queue.
So we have an array blocking queue, that's just an array
implementation of a queue.
And it blocks, what that means is if I've run out of space
in this thread here, I'm putting a for loop
that's going from 0 to 20, not including 20.
And then it's putting, I guess, 0 through 19 into that queue.
But if I only have 10 slots in the queue,
and my queue ends up being full, it
will block, which means that this put call will not return.
It'll just sit there and wait.
So you might not see the produced
output for that value of i if it's blocking.
Meanwhile, we, over here, we have a new thread
that we started up.
is our consumer, and here we have take, and this time we're going to block if the queue
is empty. So if this thread gets started before that print does and there's nothing in the
queue, it'll sit there and hang out waiting for data to come in. So that's a blocking
queue. So blocking queue handles all the synchronization, there's no manual logging.
In Java 21, they added virtual threads.
So, we have lightweight JVM managed threads.
I actually had to look this up,
because this is so far removed from what I do on a day-to-day basis,
that I had to go read up a little bit on what the heck this was.
But it made perfect sense to me,
because the same thing goes on in my day-to-day life in Scala.
So, virtual threats.
So, what we have here is,
executors is a way to get basically a thread.
So we're getting this executor service.
And then we're submitting work to the executor
and each unit, each future that we send in is,
or each unit of work that we're sending
that we're getting back as a future,
or that executes in the future,
is going to, it's actually probably returning a future here
and we're not hanging on to it because we don't care.
But because I guess it's gonna end up waiting for
all of that to complete.
Probably because, oh yeah because I think
the main program will hang.
I have to check this one, I'm not sure if this is,
I need to double check this but this is,
This would work, so if I had 100,000 operating system threads before they had virtual threads,
they're also called green threads by the way, these virtual threads.
OS, we would crash, like we would run out of memory because there's just not enough memory for that.
So, but if I'm using 100,000 virtual threads, that's fine.
Virtual threads are extremely cheap and heath allocated.
You create one per task.
So now you're allowed to create one per task.
And this is what I see in type level Scala.
I can create a virtual thread per task.
But then there's something going on behind the scenes to make it optimal.
So the JVM for these virtual threads,
the JVM is multiplexing them onto OS threads,
and they unmount transparently on blocking.
So if I end up blocking, the OS will detect that,
or the JVM, sorry, JVM will detect it,
and it will release that work
until that blocking condition has cleared,
and this is similar to the way Go works,
so Go has something called GoRoutines,
which I'm not too familiar with,
but it's the same idea as this.
So our existing blocking code would work as is.
We would want to avoid synchronized
and JNI, JNI is Java Native Interface.
that's if you're gonna call C code from Java,
which is, back when Java came out,
that was a big deal because a lot of people
had a lot of C code that they wanted to be able to use.
So if you are gonna use any of those things,
synchronized or JNI, you're gonna end up
pinning your virtual threads to an OS thread
and you're gonna just, you know,
ended up back in the same place as you started.
So you basically did things that obviated the need
the need for like the solution to sort of, it's the word I want, it's like, you, you,
you have a solution to a problem, but then you use that solution in a way that gives
you the problem back in the first place. Right. So, oh, I guess I have go routines in two
places. I was cleaning these up less because I wanted to add some stuff. All right. So,
Survey of concurrency across languages.
I keep blabbing on about sometimes,
about type levels Java.
But, that's not part of the language by itself.
Neither are actors by the way.
Actors are.
There's a framework called ACCA and ACCA has.
There's actually an open source version now,
the different name because the company that used to support it,
it's called Lightbend,
and they decided they weren't going to do that.
But in Java, I have shared memory and locks.
Threads share the heap, and I do synchronize for safety.
So that's the old school Java, like what I learned 25 years
go when I was working in a highly concurrent environment.
Scala has ACCA.
And futures is the primary thing they have built into the language.
But you can also do ACCA.
This involves message passing and we strongly prefer
immutable data.
In Rust, which I presented to you several weeks ago,
we have this ownership, and there's
something called send and sync.
When you have those are traits, the compiler
is actually enforcing rules to prevent you
to get data raised from getting data raises.
In Go, you have Go routines and channels.
So I guess the key idea here is don't communicate by sharing,
share by communicating.
I'm not a Go person, so I'll have to think a little bit
about how that, I actually got some help
building these slides by the way.
So, I got some help from Claude, actually, so I admit.
So Erlang, that's a language, that uses the actor model,
so that's the same thing as actors.
We also have actors by the way.
You can do ACCA and actors in Java as well.
But in Erlang actor model, these are lightweight processes, and there's no shared state at all in Erlang.
JavaScript has event loop and promises.
They're single threaded Async I.O. via callbacks.
In Haskell, we have software transactional memory, this is composable atomic transactions.
So this is what we have in Type Level Scala.
I always say type level is like a CASC 11, but type level is just a series of libraries.
They're built on a couple of core libraries.
So the shared memory model, Java and C, that's the lowest level approach.
Higher level models, actors, channels, software, transactional memory,
try to make concurrency safer by design.
So, why does immutability help with concurrency?
Well, if I have mutable data here and I have like thread one is trying to add data and
thread two is concurrently adding data, I might end up stopping.
Like I might try to write this in the first slot in the ArrayList.
But the other thread is also maybe trying and
might stop in the middle.
So meaning that thread might get suspended
while it's in the middle of doing it right.
And then that other thread might come in and do it right,
and then you might get half of your data
when the other thread picks up because it wrote half of the data.
Oftentimes, like a string, for example, that's multiple bytes,
and so it's not going to be able to do that atomically.
Language gives you a mechanism, synchronized or some of these other constructs.
The language gives you the ability to force it to be needed.
So if I have something like this, in Scala I have my shared, it's a list.
This is immutable.
Any thread can read it, so there are no locks needed, and
no thread can modify it, so there's no resources.
Immutable data is inherently thread-safe.
That's why functional programming and concurrency are such natural partners.
This is probably why I wanted to get deeper and deeper into functional programming.
Because it gets rid of whole classes of bugs.
So recall that the aliasing and mutation combination is the root of most concurrency bugs.
So if you think about that, in C whenever we've had memory bugs, sorry,
in Java when we have concurrency bugs, we have aliasing.
C we had aliasing and that ended up being part of the reason why we had memory bugs.
Now in Java we have aliasing and then we have code changing,
but with the expectation that the memory is still intact as it was expected.
So if we looked at this code, can anybody, well I don't expect you to, because you don't
have a lot of experience with this stuff.
This is the challenge for me, right?
So I was like, okay, where's the bug?
Oh, well, we just talked about multiple threads, right?
So multiple threads are calling this get method.
And they see that this cache,
if any one thread sees that this cache is null,
and it's going to construct a new hash panel.
And I could put my greeting in there.
Greetings, hello.
And then another thread might do that concurrently.
So I might lose.
This is a little bit weird because I think this should be key.
I think that should be key, not the string literal reading, so I think I have a bug in
the slide right?
But what could happen is two threads could call get at the same time.
Both see cache as null.
Both create a new hash map.
One thread's map and its entries is lost, so that's the problem.
So this is the check then act race commission.
This is extremely common.
So often times students write when I teach data structures one,
they write code like this.
And of course, they don't know because they have never dealt with concurrency.
So for our single threaded programs for data structures one,
it ends up being fine.
I usually point out that this is not actually thread safe,
so trying to teach them things that are just beyond what we're doing in class.
So here's a fix
This will actually say okay, I'm gonna synchronize on lazy and then dot class
So what that does is it synchronizes on the class that's loaded it's like the class definition is loaded once and
so because this is static you have to synchronize if you're gonna synchronize on
yourself. You can declare this synchronized too. Here what it's doing is
What we call double check locking and for years and years and years
So I was like told don't ever do that, don't ever do that.
They had to fix something in the JVM.
What's happening here, well, I have this map.
I'm putting my, again I have greeting,
I should have key there.
It's a little bug.
This is why we don't trust Claw, right?
So I'm updating my cache to now have .
And if I do that,
This is double check locking.
So the fast path avoids synchronization
but it's really only gonna be correct.
So back in the day, volatile was broken,
but in order to make this work,
you have to declare this volatile too.
Without it, the JVM could reorder the instructions underneath
and then that would let another thread
see a partially constructed map.
So getting concurrency right is hard.
Another reason why I like functional programming.
So we prefer higher level abstractions.
Practical guidelines for concurrent programs.
It's pretty much anything we have today, modern web servers, Gui, we prefer immutability.
Mutable objects are always going to be threats.
Minimize shared mutable state, the less sharing, the fewer bugs.
Use high level abstractions, executive service, concurrent hashmap, blocking queue, over raw
synchronized.
Don't reinvent the wheel.
Java.util.concurrent exists for a reason.
So that's the package that you want to look at if you're going to be working in Java in
a concurrent environment.
Make state ownership clear.
Who is responsible for the state?
Notice how guideline number five echoes Rust's ownership model.
Rust came out of the pain that people were dealing with.
So all of these developments in languages come out of the pain that people deal with
as they work with those things.
Java gives you the tools to write safe concurrent code, but Rust gives you guarantees about that.
So our summary.
Thread shared memory, very powerful, very dangerous.
Race conditions arise from unsynchronized access to shared mutable state.
Interorganized and locks enforce mutual exclusion but introduce deadlock risks.
Volatile ensures visibility between threads but not atomicity, atomicity is when you have
an atomic, it's something you want to happen in the problem.
Atomic classes provide lock free, thread safe operations for simple things.
The Java memory model defines happens before rules that govern what threads can see.
Higher level abstractions such as executor service, completable feature, block enqueue
reduce error prone manual synchronization.
Virtual threads in Java 21 make thread per task practical.
And immutability is the simplest path to thread safety.
Programming and concurrency are natural partners.
The concurrency landscape ranges from shared memory in Java and C
to message passing in Goerlain.
And also we can use things like ACCA to get message passing in Java.
To compile time enforcement.
So Rust will actually, the compiler will just complain at you and not compile your code
if you have memory bugs.
and that's our summary.
So I just wanted to share that with you
because I think it's interesting
if we're studying programming languages.
This is not on the final, so don't worry about it.
The topic, I will update the website,
but the stuff on Rust is also not on the final.
So I put that in there
as like enrichment bonus material
because you're studying this stuff
and maybe it's interesting to you.
It's interesting to me, that's why I stand your turn.
All right.
So, we are at 638.
I think what we'll do is, I'm gonna switch gears,
it's a little early to do the break,
so I'm gonna switch gears and we'll do the quiz
from last week and that will probably
get us close enough to break time.
And then we'll take our longer break
and you'll have time to do your evaluation.
I'm actually supposed to leave the room,
so I'll take my laptop and I'll go.
We'll get a longer break,
and then we'll just finish up with more.
I have exam review slides,
and then I also have study guide,
and we're gonna make sure to cover
all the JavaScript stuff, okay.
So,
let's start with a quiz.
All right.
Now, I have to preface all this by saying I don't spend a lot of time with JavaScript.
I had limited amount of time to prepare for JavaScript last week because I had been traveling
and stuff.
But does anybody know, remember what the answer to this one was?
And maybe we can talk about why.
I'm less of an expert on JavaScript.
But I know how to reason about what it's doing.
One way to test our understanding is to go into NodeBrain.
That was undefined.
Yes, it was.
Throws me every time.
I know why though.
No.
So if we run this,
we get undefined B, as Dylan told us.
Does anybody know why?
Any guess?
Valuable hosting.
Hoisting.
Correct.
So, again, not living,
not swimming in this pool very often for myself,
not living in this world very often,
but as soon as I looked at it,
I was like, oh, I forgot,
and then I was like, wait, wait, wait.
Var x.
What happens when we have var x?
Hoisting.
What happens, what does that mean for x?
Where is x defined?
Well, at the top.
At the top, well, the top could be out here.
Inside function.
Inside function, inside the function.
So here, inside the function.
So it's before this x equals x plus b, right?
So by putting var x here, JavaScript says, okay,
I'm going to hoist that definition, or that declaration,
of var x out here.
but the initial value is what?
Undefined.
We don't actually do the initialization to A
until we get here.
So the effect is we get this initialization
of undefined plus B.
And undefined probably ends up calling
some sort of thing that turns undefined
into the string undefined, right,
because it's concatenating.
So it's coercing the types, right?
It's casting, it's coercing.
All right, so that's why we get undefined B.
Hoisting is not your friend.
All right.
What about this one?
Anybody remember the answer to this one?
So this is where, remember last week
I said we'll never do anything with a node.
Start again.
because a lot of times these examples
have used the same variable names as before
and so if you have something left over from before,
so that's why I exited out and started Node again.
And you'll see me with JavaScript,
I'm basically always doing that
because I don't trust JavaScript.
So I think I remember the answer.
Does anybody wanna tell me what happened?
Did it work?
Did it execute?
No.
All right, why not?
I've got reference error. So, X is not defined. So, in this case, because we're using let,
there's no, well, and also, there's no definition for X above here. In the previous version,
we had that, right? We had that. So, we would have had some kind of X available, right?
Here, there's no X. That's why I exited out, by the way, because when I did the quiz,
I got the wrong answer, and I was like, oh, right, this is where I have to exit out and
start fresh right of course so there's no x defined so here it says x is not
defined so the answer is the program is not run correctly because x is not
declared when in it's first geocache.
How about this?
Let's talk about it first.
So what do we have?
We have a var f, and it's undefined initially.
And then we create a function, and we call it f.
So now we can refer to f as a function and call f.
And then I have another f equals function.
And then I have console log2, and then it calls f.
Which f does this one call when it executes?
Well down here we call f, so we're calling.
Which one?
OK, let's actually.
When we call f here at line 9, which function executes?
The one with 2 or the one with 1?
The one with 2.
The one with 2?
Okay.
I buy that.
And then inside here, which one executes?
It's self.
It executes itself.
Okay.
So do we think the answer is that it just does not terminate
because the call to F in the second anonymous function
refers to whatever the current value of F is in closing scope?
I think that's the answer.
I did all these last times.
Yeah, it goes on forever, right?
So the trick here is we can't just...
I started by asking you the question well,
in here like what f executes?
Well, we don't have static scope here, right?
We have dynamic scope, right?
And so at this point, when we're in here, f refers to itself.
But yeah, if this were not f equal function and we called f, then it would refer to something
else.
All right.
So the program does not turn open.
All right, here's a new JavaScript program.
So we have of our f, which is undefined,
then we construct a function that logs one,
and that function gets assigned to f.
And then, oh, now we're gonna update f to have this,
and this is where the syntax starts to get weird, right?
What is this?
So here I have a function
h
I think I'm passing h as a parameter, right?
Because I don't think we have type adaptations in JavaScript, right?
So when I call this function, I return a function that logs to and
then calls this function that I have to pass here.
And then I am passing in this function,
now that I've defined it, I'm passing f as my h.
Anybody see that?
So let's see if that's right.
So we think, let's look at the question.
Let me think.
What is printed to the console when the program is executed?
So at this point I have this function that is this whole thing.
And now I call f, and oh yeah, I'm returning a function, right?
So that's why this set of parens invokes this internal function.
So it should print two.
And then it should call h and print one.
And let's see what it does, because I'm going to have to go.
The way I talked it out, though, that's the reasoning.
Oh, boy.
How do I cancel?
And it does 2-in-1.
And the undefined happens because it's printing 2-in-1,
and then this line of code ends up evaluating .
But that's not part of the answer.
So two on the first line and one on the second line.
This one, okay.
What do we remember or think about this one?
Which of the following expressions cause done to be printed on the console?
so if I have F, which I have defined as this function,
and then inside I have these nested functions,
how many times do I have to do this thing
to invoke functions in order to get to the point
where this line executes?
I think it's five.
I think you're right.
One, two, three, four, five.
All right, so let's, that's like the one that I thought was easy.
So F.
Actually, I'll take.
You know what I'll do?
F, notice that doesn't do it, right?
That doesn't do it.
That was the same one.
All right, I went too far.
Earlier, that one worked.
My I went right to the undefined and skipped it.
So it's the one that has five.
And you can actually count how many, it's like, okay, well,
So if I'm invoking F and then that's returning a function, and then I'm invoking F again,
and then I'm invoking.
So if you keep counting these, you end up with five points.
Let's submit and see how we did.
Five out of five.
All right.
So here we go.
Still a little early for the break.
So this wasn't as bad as I thought.
Let's do the JavaScript from the study guide.
Let's do that before the break, or at least start it.
There's four questions on the study guide that were JavaScript.
Let me open up the study guide.
So the first one we'll look at is number 7.
Now, sometimes the study guide questions are the same as the quits, so if that happens,
then .
Yes, okay.
So, instead of inheritance, like we have in static languages where we define a class
hierarchy, static ,
We use delegation between objects.
So it's kind of like you have a linked list of objects that form your delegation chain.
And if you are an object, then you're what we would call super class in a static language
is the prototype, right?
And then you can keep following these prototype links, the proto-links actually in the case
of objects.
keep following these links and you can actually change them at runtime.
Okay.
I'm just reading through the field was automatically initialized when using
new together with a constructor function that offers prototype object.
JavaScript objects and the links between them can be updated dynamically.
So, let's look at this JavaScript code.
have a function box.
Box, we can set boxes prototype.
So this is dynamically saying my superclass
now has a get x function, which returns this.x.
And then I have let b is new box 2.
And I'm logging b.getx.
And then I have B dot Y equals three.
So I'm adding a property Y, I think.
I'm talking about, I did not prepare these questions,
let's see what happens.
Then I have a new box four and I say C dot get X.
And then I changed my prototype for C to be B,
And then I call this c dot y, so I have y here.
And then I have box.prototypeC, and
I'm setting that equal to 5, and then I log c dot z.
And question asks, what is printed to the console
when this code is executed?
So you think it's letter C?
Yeah.
2, 4, 3, 5.
So let's see.
The first thing is, this get x, right?
So that would give us two.
And then we have y and then we have C as in box.
X, okay.
And then we set the prototype of C to B.
And then we call C dot y.
And that should be three, did I skip a,
Oh, I skipped a get x, didn't I?
I skipped a get x.
So, sorry.
So that get x should give me 4, right?
Because that is the x that we have in this separate box.
By the way, we're calling new, so that's constructing an object, right?
It's not just invoking a function.
We're calling new.
So that's why we had 2, 4, and then 3 here.
Because here, we set the prototype to b.
And we don't have a Y on C.
So, what the delegation chain, what JavaScript does is it looks at the prototype.
And so that's how it gets the three.
And then we set the boxes prototype to have a property Z is five.
And then I look to get the five out.
So, I agree with you.
I think it's C.
And sure enough, the answer is C.
It might help to draw this out, like if you're looking at this.
That's why I give you scrap paper on exam, you can draw this out.
Remember that you have to follow the proto link to search the parent object,
parent in quotes, because it's not like a super class,
like in our statically typed languages that I'm mostly comfortable.
So if we tried some of these variations,
anybody tried the variations?
Change b dot y equals three,
b dot c equals three.
We can try some of them out.
Let's do that and see what that ends up meaning.
So I'm going to fire up, in order to do this,
well, because I think it's working.
I'm going to take the code and copy it here.
And then for each variation, I'll just change out each thing.
I have to get rid of those pesky line numbers.
Some editors have, like, vertical cursors.
Which is much nicer in cases like this.
I'm gonna get rid of all this.
Let's actually take the original code and just pop it in.
Sometimes this thing will ends up printing out other things.
So I'm going to change all the console logs statements.
Because those are the ones we care about.
So what I'll do is I'll say log.
I'm going to do that.
I hope that works, because I think sometimes we're getting,
it's just printing out stuff as we go.
All right.
So let's.
Start again.
So we're looking for this is the initial code.
So we have 2435.
Notice these other, like it's printing out three here
because we were updating the topic.
So I did that, added those log colon things just
to illustrate what we're seeing out of the jump.
So now we're going to change.
We're going to change B.y equals three to B.z equals three.
So we will now change.
I think I can comment with that.
B.z equals three.
So this time we got two, four, undefined, and three.
So the third one we got was undefined.
Why is that?
Oh, I might actually do A, B, C, D. It'll be easier to spot.
I do this sometimes when I'm debugging manual, so that should be deep.
I just want to see, like, if my eye will more easily find what I'm looking for.
So a log 2 and then b log 4 and then c log undefined and then d is 3.
So y is c undefined as c.
Ah yes, because we don't have a y, right?
So it's pretty straightforward.
Now we're going to remove b dot y .
changing it we're gonna remove it all together. So by commenting it I'm getting
the removal.
So in this case I got two, four, undefined, five.
and that's because here there's nothing in y.
Same idea.
Something that's not defined is going to come out as undefined.
We have two more.
Box.prototype.z equals 5 to box.prototype.y equals 5.
is 5. So here we have a box dot prototype, I put this back actually, to
the initial. That's b dot y.
Yeah.
Hold on, something looks funny. Box dot prototype dot c.
Oh it's down there.
Box number of cubes, y equals 5.
Next, this time we got a log 2, b log 4, c log 3, d log undefined.
So here our z is undefined.
It was like a new line.
And that's because we changed this line to B.Protect.ly.
And then finally you remove BoxNetProtect.
Just remove it altogether so if you do that.
So I didn't comment on this topic.
We're just removing that one.
That was what I replaced it to.
Yeah.
Just delete that.
This time we got 2, 4, 3, and also .
So that makes sense, because we didn't define it.
That just illustrates how the delegation chains work.
That was seven.
Let's do, let's do eight.
This is also delegation-based OOP.
So this talks about object literals, right?
So object literals have this defined
properties between .
Braces.
It's kind of weird, unfortunate.
Because code blocks are also delimited by braces.
So you have to carefully inspect whether it's
with the context.
Are the braces blocks of statements
or do they enclose a comma separated list of key value
pairs?
In other languages, accessing fields and methods
from within an object requires this.
But we might need it here.
Whenever we attempt to access a field that is not
present in an object, JavaScript will return undefined.
And sometimes it will throw exceptions
rather than reportings.
There's no compiler here.
It's interpreted.
So we have this JavaScript code.
So what does this function f, when we invoke it,
what does it return?
And the function.
It returns what?
Returns n add the get function.
Returns n and get function but what is that inside?
It returns the value of n.
Well, what I'm looking for is, what is this whole,
like n and get your get function exist within something.
What does it exist within?
They're grouped in something.
They're properties of something.
Okay.
If we look at the top of the screen,
at the top of the page,
object literals.
That's an object literal.
So, the function is returning an object literal
that has a property n that has a value of zero.
and a property get which is a function that returns this .
Function G has a var N and
then it returns an object literal that just has a get function,
get property in that function.
So identify all the statements that are true.
F1.n, is that return undefined or throw an exception?
So F1.n.
Shorter than 0.
So F1.n should return a 0, you're saying.
So that would make number one false, right?
So that would not be true.
G1.n.
So what happens with G1.n?
So G1, we're gonna invoke G.
We're gonna give back this object and we're gonna try to call n.
Is that return undefined or throw an exception?
Should return undefined?
Should return undefined.
I, I agree with that.
I agree with that.
We'll have to check right?
But I'm, I'm going with that.
F1 dot get so, so far 2 is true, right?
So F1 dot get returns undefined or throw an exception.
So F1 gives us this object here and we call function get.
And we have this dot n.
Do we think that returns undefined or throws an exception?
Sure, it returns 0, too.
I think it returns 0, too.
because I think this dot n makes it be this one that we've defined here.
So far, still, we only have two.
Number two is the one.
G1 dot get.
So G1 dot get.
I think that one is going to do something,
because I think the n here doesn't know what n it is by the rules of JavaScript,
the scoping rules of JavaScript.
So I think that's also true, right?
So G1, so far we have two and four, two and four are true.
And then five, the N used by G1 and G2 is shared between them.
No way.
Do you see any common N between the two?
They're all separate, right?
So I think the answers are gonna be two and four.
And I'm gonna choose this.
Yes it is, let's see.
So number eight.
oh it looks like we got eight all right I am wrong so number eight the answer I
have is D well let's see let's talk about why so it's only two so excellent
I am going to now remove all the line numbers.
Isn't this funny?
This is where I say to my students I don't have to remember all this.
You do.
What I can give you is the explanation for what we are looking at a problem.
But it's your job to make sure you understand.
And one of my friends, he says JavaScript
is the worst language ever.
He's not wrong.
And somebody in class last week said,
people who designed this language should be in prison.
I'm like, this is crazy.
So how do I have an extra brace?
oh.
That's the function.
I'm returning.
Oh, I see.
I forgot.
I don't have extra breaks.
I forgot to index.
All right.
Let's try these out for a little bit.
So we have f1.n returns undefined or frozen exception.
What's going on here?
F1?
You didn't declare the variables.
Oh, right.
That's why.
Thank you, John.
No problem.
That's why it's undefined because F1 doesn't exist.
OK.
For F1 equals, I guess I have to, why don't I do all of those, right?
Yeah.
Let's just do them all.
I'm going to add it here.
Add it here.
Get rid of the line numbers.
You certainly get separate, different answers
if you don't do this part right.
All right, so F1 dot n does not return undefined,
throw an exception, g1.n, undefined, so 2, I think maybe the answer key is wrong, f1.get
gives me 0. So that's not true. This is where we were before, right? So the next one is g1.get.
Oh that one returns 0.
So this is weird.
So the answer is 2.
Oh I see, okay.
And then the n used by g1 and g2 is shared between.
Well that's not true, we know that.
So the one we were wrong on, was 4?
Yeah.
So let's look at that.
why g1.get returns undefined or through as an exception.
So I guess then what happens if I, well let's do this.
So I'll go g1 dot, n equals 42, and then I'll say g1 dot get zero.
It's closing, it must be closing over this, right.
It must be closing, because I tried to change.
Did I do that right?
The question asked?
Okay, all right.
So I also screwed up one more thing that I was,
the answer that we got was correct for this part, this last one.
But I'm gonna talk about that in a minute because I was forgetting that it wasn't
asking about F and G, it was asking about two different things.
But what's happening is it's closing the open.
So it's creating a closure.
I feel like I've said this before.
It's because I taught this last word.
I feel like I hit the same thing.
So this g1.n is just useless.
That didn't help us.
Does everybody see that?
So what happened here is that in this one,
there is a very subtle difference.
And this one here, the get function
is defined as part of an object, just like it is here.
but the n here, if I change this to not have the word this here,
then it wouldn't be able to find n because it doesn't,
it doesn't, the way JavaScript works is that n,
it doesn't know to look at this, right?
In this one, because we created an object and referred to a free variable n,
We got a closure.
It was a very, very subtle difference there.
At least now I can explain it.
This is not stuff I look at.
All right.
Wait, so why does g1.n return undefined?
g1.
Well, it's g1.get, right?
Wait, didn't we say it was d?
Like 2, that's true?
g1.n.
So the answer is D, so number two is true.
G1 dot n.
Oh, am I getting confused?
Thank you for calling me out.
Let me see.
Let me try it.
G1 dot n.
All right, let's try the whole thing again.
Nope.
Helps if I go in the right place.
All right.
So we said G1.n is returning undefined.
So it is not closing.
Okay.
And it would not have...
So it wouldn't have a this.n either.
Okay.
So I'm getting like all of these things mixed up.
So yes, thank you for calling that out.
So g1.get...
Oh, sorry.
Okay, we got two things going on here.
g1.n is undefined, right?
Because that object doesn't have...
The object we got back doesn't have a property named n.
The question asks g1.get.
In that case, I get a 0.
Why doesn't it have a property called n?
Is it because var n equals zero isn't a property?
It's not a property of this object that we got back when we invoked g.
Oh, because it's not in the return.
Yes, it's not in the object here.
And we didn't add it later.
If we had added an n later, it would be a different n.
But at the time that this function was constructed,
the interpreter said, oh, I have a free variable n.
And so by the way that JavaScript works,
it says that the reference to n here is going to be closed.
So it created a closure.
Did that clear it up?
Yeah, I don't really know JavaScript all that well.
No, I don't either.
All right.
Feel free to play around with these and ask questions in the Discord.
So we have some variations.
So if we look at the solution strategy, maybe that gives us a little hint, right?
So notice that each of the functions returns an object.
Some declare local variables before returning the object.
When this is present, look for a field in the same object.
Otherwise, look for a local variable.
So that local variable would be that g case.
We had a local variable, and that's what this is.
If it's not present, it's undefined.
Every time a function is called, new local variables are placed on the stack and added to closures if accessed from the returned object.
So we could change return this.n and function f to return n.
If we do that, we just return n.
It doesn't know to look for the property, so I'm going to take that code.
Oops, I got to go into node again.
Alright.
And now f1.get is gonna give me uncaught reference error because n is free in there.
In the code here, this n, the way this works, it doesn't look at this.
In Scala, it would automatically look at this, but in JavaScript it doesn't.
Who made up these rules?
I don't know, I don't know why.
This language is crazy.
And then f1.n would return on the file as well?
as well? F1.n? No, that wouldn't return undefined because it's a property on F1.
We didn't change that. We just changed how the function implementation was.
Good question. Alright, let's look at the other one. So the other variation.
Change return n in function g to return this dot n. Alright, so we'll go over here and
we'll change and put this back, because this was this dot n. We're going to change this
to this.n. What do we think that'll do? I agree with that because this.n refers
to a property end in this object that we're defining here. And the end we have
is closed and it's not this. Let's see what happens. So this one we need to do
What do we have to do with g1.get?
Yeah.
Undefined, right?
Now, the last point here, item five, the end used by g1 and g2 is shared between them.
So why is that not true?
Remember g1 and g2 both are objects returned by function g, right?
So why is that one not true?
Anybody know how to explain that?
Every time I invoke g, I get a new var n, right?
So if I invoke g once and get a var n and then return this object,
which closes over n.
I'm closing over that initial n, which
means I copy that environment, whatever's there.
And then I invoke it again and I get a new n.
So that's why they're not shared.
So earlier I glossed over because my eye failed
to see that I wasn't talking about f and g.
But f and g aren't shared either, right?
Because there's no crossover.
But the ones from g, you get a different instance of n,
different occurrence.
Okay, good.
So, 25 after.
So, you're getting 25 minutes to take a nice long break and also please do your course evaluation.
I'm supposed to give you time for the class to do it.
So, do that and then we'll pick it up at 7.50 and we'll just do a review for the rest of the night.
And I will get out of here.
Take my coffee.
And now I'm going to change the color by the way.
I'm going to change the color.
If I can change the color of the color, I'm going to change the color color of the color color.
This is a simple recipe that I use for a long time.
It's very easy to use.
We use this recipe to do this recipe.
We use this recipe to use the recipe for a long time.
I use this recipe for a long time.
This recipe is not always easy to use.
I'm gonna go through this.
I'm gonna go through it.
So, I'll try it.
So, this is the first time to look at the dressing room.
And I will show you how to make the dressing room.
It's hard to make the dressing room.
But it's hard to make the dressing room as I go.
I'm going to put the oil on my back.
I'm going to make sure that you have to use a bunch of different types, so you'll be working on that.
So, the first thing I wanted to do is make sure that you're not going to use this, you know,
the first thing I wanted to do is make sure that you have to get your own product.
Let's do it.
And the second one is going to be there.
Here we go.
Thank you.
so
All right.
This is a good idea of a great feeling, but we also have a lot of fun and fun.
I'll show you the next video.
It's delicious!
I'm going to get the best of the time.
Now, if you have any options,
you can have a couple of times
and you can use this as well as your own.
I'm going to get a full list of the other side.
It's so good to get started.
I'll see you next time.
All right.
Here are the original items that we have on the top of the top.
And I'll let you in the next video.
This is the first step.
Okay.
I wanted to use this one.
Here you can see the same color.
The color is so good.
This color is very good.
Thank you.
Okay.
.
Now, let's go.
I'm going to put a little on the top.
I'm going to put it on top.
I'm going to put it on top of the top.
...
Okay.
Thank you.
What about a nice piece of paper?
I don't know.
It's a good piece of paper.
I look at it.
I'm going to put it on the paper.
All right.
Now I'm going to cut the disc on the actual side.
I'm going to cut on the side here and then I'm going to cut off the side of the side.
I'm going to cut the side of the side.
Thank you.
so
So, here we go.
Perfect.
Thank you.
...
That's it.
So let's go.
Thank you.
That's how I feel!
This is the easiest way to do this!
I want you to use the appropriate way to do this!
I want you to use this as well!
This is an appropriate way to do this!
Thank you.
So I'm going to go to the mini,
so I'm going to go to the mini.
I'm going to go to the mini.
I'll do it.
Now I'm going to take a mini.
I'm going to go to the mini.
so
Thank you.
And the next step, the right step is to put the water into the water.
It will take a long time.
It will be the next step.
The right step is to get the water.
The water is a little less in the water.
So, the water is like water.
All right.
of this place, and get it finished out.
All right, so we just finished eight.
Two more JavaScript questions so we should do those from the study guide.
The next one I have is 22.
So this talks about function scope versus block scope.
So function scope is var.
Remember, we get hoisting.
So hoisting puts it at the beginning of the function.
So that is why we call it that.
And block scope is let.
You also have const, right?
So, variables declared in function scope are always at the top.
While the initialization remains as an assignment in that location,
in that place, this can make a surprising effect together with closures.
Okay, so we have this JavaScript code.
So, consider the following JavaScript code with alternative variable
declaration keyword.
So here we have, inside our function, we have var fs here.
And then we have a for loop.
And then we have var x.
So that gets hoisted, right, to the beginning of the function.
So var x actually exists up here and then over here
on the far right actually you have let x equals i.
This is actually, should maybe be commented out,
but this is intended to say
you're not actually doing both of these.
Like you're doing one of these lines, okay?
And then you are calling push on an array,
which is gonna actually push an object onto this array.
That will push, I guess, this function object,
which will return x.
So the question asks,
how does the behavior change with var versus let?
So, down here we call console log.
And we have f at zero, so that's the thing that we pushed here.
Okay, so remember that the two square braces is gonna be an empty array in JavaScript,
and the push method will add the new element to the right hand side of the array.
And then the question asks, what is printed to the console when this code is executed?
So, this is testing your understanding of closures and far and let.
All right.
So, what happens when we execute this code?
So, we're getting the function out and we're invoking it.
So, when we have var x equal i, what do we print?
Okay, why?
Because of hoisting.
So x is gonna be defined up here, right?
And we will always be updating x equal i.
But then, when the function actually executes,
it's gonna refer back to that x, right?
and that same x is shared across all of them.
So that's why you're always going to get 4.
Does everybody follow that?
So I agree with that.
Okay, when we change it to let x equal i,
what do we end up getting?
Zero.
Right. So I agree with that, so let's talk about why that is. So how many
elements are we actually pushing onto the array? Five, because we're inside this
for loop, right? So we're inside this for loop we're pushing five different
functions each of which are returning x which if we change that to let we're
defining that as block scope right so that x is scoped here it's defined here
and so returning x is going to end up with it's going to close over that x
that we had defined here and so the zero of element of the array
it's a function, but it will return 0.
And the first element, the element at 1 will return 1.
The element at 2 will return 2 and so on.
So that's why the answer here is going to end up being 0,
because we're accessing the 0 of the element.
So I agree with that, and the answer key agrees with that.
22A.
All right.
So the solution strategy.
You know, look at the code var x equals i, move var x to the top of the function,
and then leave the x equal i in the place that it's at, and then evaluate the code.
So do the hoisting in your head, essentially.
For let, you don't do any hoisting, because there's no hoisting with let.
You leave that let x equal i in place, and then you evaluate the code.
Okay.
So what are our variations here?
So let's see.
So if we remove far i equals x and just directly access i
from the function, what happens?
Same thing or something different?
Shall we test it out?
Should be 5, I guess.
Should be 5.
Yes, I agree with that.
Should we check test it out to see?
Tell us why you think five?
You're directly accessing i over there.
And since i has been already incremented, it gets the five.
Yeah, so.
I think that would be good.
comment that out
I did it again.
I have my, there we go.
All right, so there's my function and then.
shouldn't the return x be return i for the variation?
I haven't done the variation yet.
You're right, I'm not there yet.
So I was gonna just, let's first execute it as it was,
just to confirm our understanding.
It doesn't like that.
Let me do wrong.
No, we haven't declared x, I guess.
Oh.
Hmm.
Oh, right, right, right, because I was messing around with the code, right?
So we start off, that's how it should be.
I did that, and then I forgot that I had done that.
Oh, and then I have to go into node.
All right, this time, no, it doesn't like that either.
What's going on?
It's weird.
Let's just try.
Oh.
Did I get it on?
Did I screw it up?
Let's try again.
Let's just see if that's the solution.
I don't trust myself.
So maybe I'm just going too fast.
So this part is what's weird, right, because we're changing this.
So what I was trying to do was comment out that.
Oh, and this is inside the for loop.
OK, so that.
And then end the for loop.
And then.
I hope I'm not crazy.
Maybe the question's bad.
I still don't like that, so why?
How do I get it?
How am I getting a brace that's off?
Am I not copying...
Oh, I know it's wrong.
We need to define the name of the function.
So that's a typo in the question, right?
That would obviously be a typo in the question.
Let's try that again.
I don't have to exit out because I'm never going to find anything.
Oh, there we go.
All right.
So now what happens when we execute?
Oh, I get it.
It's not really a typo.
It's saying you have this code and it's not really, it's sort of a typo, right?
Like it's not, you couldn't actually copy and paste it and run it.
But now we've defined it.
So we're gonna say that.
So we have four.
So this time we had var, so we got four.
That's what we expected.
Right?
And then if we change it to let.
And just pop arrow.
Change it to let.
This time we should see.
zero right that's what we said and now the question this the variation is
remove the var x equal i and just directly x is i so to do that we'll remove the var or the let
that we had, and we'll just change this to reference i, right?
Yeah.
So we do that.
Oh no.
It's like, that's ridiculous.
OK.
We'll do it the old school way.
So take this out.
I'll just copy and paste it.
Oh, and again, node.
All right, and now we'll call it F, and we get 5.
And that's what we said, right?
That's what we got.
Because it's referencing I, and I is going to be at the end of the for loop,
when the for loop exits, the value of I will be 5.
Right.
so the condition fails, so the forward loop exited, and then by the time we got to that thing below,
the i that it's referencing is always the same i, which is defined for that whole forward loop.
Okay.
And then change the 4 to let and then directly access i.
So again, we don't have an x, so instead of this, we have let, right?
We do that.
We get.
In that case, we got zero.
Because let is going to scope it to that.
to that iteration of the body of the foregoop.
So different scoping rules.
So that's 22.
And finally, we'll do 31 and then I have a set of slides to cover the whole course.
the golf.
31.
So here we have free variables.
We have these variables that are neither parameters of the function nor
local variables of the function body.
And they may be bound to variables in the functions of the environment.
And when we have an environment, we're talking about closures.
So a closure is a data structure that combines a function with the variables
from the environment to make them available on function execution.
In JavaScript, all variables are mutable.
There's no such thing as immutability in JavaScript.
So there is no decision whether variables should be copied or referenced.
For simplicity, we're gonna use effectively final variables and
not modify them in the environment once they are initialized.
Okay, so here we have JavaScript code.
We have a function f that takes a parameter j.
We have far n, which we're gonna set to be the value that we had for j.
And then f is gonna return a function that takes a parameter i.
And will return an object that has a get function that
takes, that tries to take n and
increment by i and update n and return it.
So then we have below that we have some statements.
Lots of statements.
And the question asks what output will be logged in the console and the clue is executed.
All right.
So g is gonna be f , x is gonna be g , and y is gonna
to be g . All right. So when we call f , what do we get back? We get back a function
that takes an i, whatever i is, and it does this thing. So if we call ... well, the good
thing is we have no undefined in the answer, right? So that's a clue that we don't have
don't have to worry about that case, so that's helpful.
So if we have g, we end up, we have a function, and that function takes an i.
So down below, we call oh, in the next line,
we call g .
So then in that case, we should be getting back six.
Yeah.
Is that what you think?
I think we get back 6 for the first one.
The next one we should be getting back 8.
Why 8?
Why not 7?
Because n is getting shared between x and y.
So that's why, well let's say,
previously we were 6 and when we increment it,
by 2 we get 8 back.
So yeah, so the previous increment,
incremented, 5 to 6, right, and then because we had 6,
then we add 2 and we get 8.
So the key here is that, we call f once, right, so we have 1n.
and then f returned the function. But that function uses a, has a closure, it's closed over that n,
so that n is copied into that closure. But then it's shared by f, by all invocations of f. Every
time you invoke f it's always referring to that same n. So when we invoke g, which is the function
we got back, its n is the same as when we invoke g the next time, right? And so x.get,
we get 6. y.get, we get 8. And there you have the answer, right, because by process
of elimination. Let's just confirm that we understand x.get again will increment by 1,
right, and give us 9. And then y.get will increment by 2 and give us 11. So the answer
is D, and that is what I have on the answer key. So yeah, that makes sense to me.
So let's check the variation. What if we change F to immediately return the object of the
anonymous nested function? So we would have, let's take, all right, let's do that.
I've taken all this code, I will copy it.
All right, now I gotta just get rid of line numbers.
Oh, and again, I have this here, so I can go over the line number, so we can do it.
And again I have to indent.
It doesn't seem to preserve my indents.
Like, you know, when I have two indents,
it doesn't seem to do that very well.
What's going on here?
Do like a guy.
Oh again, right.
We have some nesting going on.
That one's OK.
And then this one, more nesting.
More nesting.
Look.
Wow.
There we go.
All right.
So the variation, let's just do the initial, just to confirm that we're not crazy.
Because whenever I do JavaScript, I feel like I'm going .
So we've got 6, 8, 9, 11, and that was where we said the answer was D.
And then we're going to say change f to immediately return the object of the anonymous nested
function, so that's this.
So I'm going to take this to immediately return, so what does that look like?
I guess that means we replace all this with that. I'll indent it, but I'll leave it on one line.
Oh, well, that's interesting.
So I guess what that means is that I would
need to preserve the get, right?
So the get implementation would be the same.
So that's what the question intends.
So let me just fix that up.
I didn't do that right.
Something's off.
Let's fix it.
Chosen is your friend.
Thank you for having a snack in the editor.
Thank you.
So, let's just check it out.
Let me show you how it's going.
for having a stack of the editor.
There, Control-Z is your friend.
Okay, so we need to keep that.
So instead of, okay, it's better
if I just read the question and it makes sense of it.
Let's get rid of that.
And then let's, what did it say?
bar N equals J, so we have F
function f of j.
All right. We're going to do this in two steps. First we're going to take that.
So f is going to immediately return
That. So return, I think we got to take that now.
Or is this a separate J? It's really hard to make sense of that, right?
Function fj bar n equals j.
I think it's that.
Not sure.
Return, we're returning an object,
and then we've got this get thing.
and the get thing is gonna be the same.
So we'll just paste that in.
And I don't know if it intended to have a j here,
another j, right, because of the way it's worded.
There's no i declaration.
There's no i.
Oh.
I feel like the variationist doesn't have enough information.
Yeah.
It's almost like a badly worded variation.
Well, I think we should then just move on.
Because we're all looking at it, we're all like, what does this variation even mean?
Change f to immediately return the object of the anonymous nested function.
I mean that could mean that you're calling new, but it doesn't say that.
So I don't know what this means.
Alright, let's skip that.
But we got the main question, we understand that, so we understand what it's getting at.
Great, we got 45 minutes left.
Let us go.
So I hope you're having fun with JavaScript.
I certainly am not.
I don't like that language.
I really don't like that language.
So we have some slides here, about 36 slides.
I don't know if we're going to get through these.
If we don't get through all these,
we did a lot with JavaScript today,
so that's at the end, so at least that's good.
Let's go back into the land of where we're comfortable.
So I'll try to go through these and try
to get through as many as possible.
So is F recursive?
Yes.
Is?
Do you disagree?
No, no, I disagree.
Oh, okay.
So F, and it's recursive because it's calling itself, right?
So we're back in Skala land, and is it tail recursive?
I heard a no.
I agree with that, why?
Because after F returns,
the recursive call returns,
what do you have to do with the result?
You have to multiply by N.
Where does N live?
It's in the stack frame for your invocation of F.
If you didn't have that here,
you have nothing in
the stack frame that's special that you need,
and that's how tail recursion works.
like you, as long as you don't have work to do.
It's not tail recursive.
Okay, how about g?
Is g recursive?
Yes because it calls itself right?
Is it tail recursive?
No.
No, because you have to do this multiplication after G returns.
And actually, first you call F, you get the result, you store that in some temporary location.
Then you call G, you get the result, and then you do the multiplication right away.
Okay.
H. Is H recursive?
Yes.
Is H tail recursive?
Correct.
Notice there's nothing here that you need.
Once you call g, you get something back.
You call f, you get something back and
then those two parameters get passed to h and
there's nothing more that has to be done when h returns.
There's no additional work to do.
So h is tau recursive.
Is i recursive?
No.
And so if it's not recursive, it can't be tau recursive either, right?
So there's the answers. F is recursive but not tail recursive. G is recursive but not tail recursive. H is tail recursive. The recursive call to H is last and I is not recursive at all.
Continuation passing, ooh, fun one.
Fill in the blanks in the continuation passing style.
So if I took this function and I wanted to convert it, it's a factorial function,
I want to convert it to continuation passing, how do I do that?
So what does this do?
this is factorial, so if n less than or equal one, then return one.
Otherwise, take n and multiply by the result of calling recursively with n minus one.
So our state is essentially like this thing here.
So if n is less than or
equal to 1, then we return something that's holding the result.
And otherwise, we call xcp,
I'm going to just bring up the answer.
Right. So, let's think about it.
So, to make it a continuation passing we have to have a continuation which is a function.
So here we have big int, it's a function from big int to x.
So I have to call k of 1, I see, x is here.
In fact, CPS, if I'm bigger than one, then I subtract one,
until I get to one. But my continuation is this function here. So I get an r and then I pass
k of n times r. So this is converting this factorial, this multiplication that's happening
here. It's now happening here in the continuation. So that is the continuation passing style.
You have some memory that's declared out here.
Actually this is just passing a function, right?
So how would you, for this you would just use the identity, right?
K of 1, right?
If n less or equal 1, the answer is 1.
So we would need k of 1 to return 1.
All right.
Ooh, see.
Scope and life's dangling.
Is p pointing to the heap or the stack?
So p is a pointer to an int, we got that pointer from calling f.
And we call f, we return the address of x,
which was the parameter we passed in.
So it's P pointing to the heap for the stack?
Stack.
I agree with that.
Tell me why.
The frame of F holds the address of X.
So whatever X value stored in the stack of F is,
basically we are returning that.
So that's why I just-
You're close.
Your language is not precise enough.
So X is stored in the stack frame.
So you said frame, so that's what you meant, right?
But that's minor.
X is stored in the stack frame.
But it's returning the address of that.
It's not returning the value.
So just be very, very clear about that in your mind.
So yes, if you dereference that pointer,
you might get the value that was there, but you might not, because P is dangling or not.
Is P dangling or not?
It is dangling.
What happens when F exits?
It is freed, but it gets to a point of doing.
Yes, you could say it's freed.
The stack frame is popped.
Yeah.
So that memory is no longer valid, it's no longer live memory.
And C will let you do this thing and then if you try to dereference P, it is not safe.
So does P need to be freed?
Yes.
manually?
By you the programmer?
Do you need to type free P?
If it was on the stack frame and the stack frame got popped...
Do you have to do that?
No.
No!
Right, so you don't have to free it manually, you don't have to type in free p.
How about q?
Let's look at q.
So q ends up being, well we have to invoke g.
So we invoke g, we pass 5.
We allocate an int on the stack, sorry, on the heap.
Whenever you see malloc you're on the heap.
So we allocate an integer on the heap,
and then we treat it as an int pointer, pointer to an int.
And then we say, OK, I'm going to take my x value
and copy it into the memory location that y is referencing,
And then I'm going to return a copy of, I'm sorry,
I'm going to return y, which is the pointer to the end.
All right.
So is q pointing to the heap or the stack?
Heap.
I agree with that.
Is q dangling?
No.
Because we allocated it.
We didn't free it.
So it's dereferencing it as safe.
Does q need to be freed?
So whenever you see malloc you've got to see it free.
You've got to have a corresponding free.
So again, P points to the stack in the first one.
Dangling, dereferencing, not safe.
P points to already freed memory.
Q however points to the heap.
It's not dangling.
It can be dereferenced and it must be freed.
Okay, more unsafe memory access.
So does this program make an unsafe memory access?
So let's analyze this program.
So we're going to call F.
So F is going to take a pointer to an int.
It's going to increment the value that's stored in that location.
And then it's going to return that pointer.
So if I pass the address of x, I can print the result.
Oh, I can get the result, which is a pointer, and then dereference it.
And then that's an integer.
So that's so far so good.
If I do the same with y, ooh, this is a little bit weird, right?
So I've got an address of a double that I'm treating now as a pointer to an int.
And then I'm accessing it, so unsafe. So let's see what does the slide say.
So it makes an unsafe memory access when dereferencing x because it accesses memory
that stores a double as if it were an int. So that is the first place. And then it also
is going to return a pointer to an end. Well, it's already broken. Once you hit there, you've hit this
undefined behavior. You've already entered into a, I said once, I think that, you know, when you do
this in C, it's no longer C, right? It's whatever the compiler decided to do. Okay.
Option types. So I have a class person with a name and an email. My email is optional.
I may or may not have an email for any given person. So if I invite that person
and I'm going to send email to do the invitation, so I'll check to see, okay, what cases do I need
to have, I have an option for email, so what cases do I need to cover?
None and what?
String or ?
Who's a name for it?
So the opposite of none is?
Sum.
Yeah.
So I might have a none, and I might have a sum.
And what's the type of the thing that sum would contain?
You just said it.
String.
String, right.
So in order to write this code, what does it look like?
So I'm going to just write the inside there.
So I have case none, right?
Case sum.
When I have case sum, what goes in here?
This is gonna be that unapplied thing that's in your textbook.
I'm going to basically bind here.
So, I'm gonna bind to some variable that I define here.
So I'm gonna call it eml, no,
because I'm doing that on purpose because email here is that,
so I'm just doing that to be clear.
Okay, so in the case of none, so let's see.
Depending on whether P has an email address.
If there's no email address, you can't do anything, right?
So the return type of this thing is Boolean, so
So we have to say false.
We have a mail sender.
So here now we have the email.
So we just say mail sender EML.
Because that takes a string and returns a Boolean.
So we get back the Boolean and so we have satisfied the contract of
the return type of this particular method.
Oh, okay, so then, what is this?
Send an email to a person P, we did that one.
Return the email address of a person P as a string or
unknown if they don't have an address.
Okay, how would that one work?
and it's one line of code so how do we do that in one line of code
get or else on invite
say again
yeah
p.email.getforelse
I think you can also do P dot email dot fold.
Maybe fold.
I'm going to do some live code again.
I closed it.
I hated JavaScript so much that I closed it.
And I love JavaScript so much that I'm typing Node because of habit.
I want to type Scala.
So I'm going to define my person.
So I'm going to say person, Val, Eric equals new person, Eric, that's me.
eric dot folksum
Alright, there's me, so if I say eric dot
email
so if we say get or else unknown
that should work
eric dot
email
not fold unknown.
I think this works.
Yeah, that works too.
So you can say fold.
So fold, what I did here, I was testing to see
if my memory was working.
So what fold does for an option is if you have an option
and it's none, it returns whatever value you provide
in this first parameter list.
So you can put unknown here.
And then the type of this part, so if I use string here,
then I did the brace thing, because I'm used to Scala 2,
but you can also do colon and indent on the next line.
But what this is going to be here is going to be a function.
this function you could say X arrow X because this is going to get this is
gonna find X to whatever is in the sum and then you're returning that or what I
did was I just did identity which is Scala's way of basically doing X arrow
X I just wanted to show off the full thing most people don't do that
So that's all coding style stuff.
And there's the answers, okay.
So get or else is the way the slides have it.
And this shows you how to do, so this uses curating.
This is another way to do invite without the case analysis.
So you do p, it's the same idea, p.email, but now you're gonna,
instead of fold, I did map, right?
So, forget or else, I did map.
So I map and I'm using the, I'm taking advantage of currying.
So what happens when I call, when I pass this function here like this?
Well, it actually, remember map, this parameter here is a function, right?
So what it does is it actually applies this function to the string that's there
in a non-empty option.
So it will call mail sender and return whatever that returns or get or else false.
And there's a way you can do it with fold as well.
Static versus dynamic scope.
So this asks you to think about this code which looks like Scala code, it's using the
syntax of Scala code, but it asks you to think about it in terms of static scoping and or
dynamic scoping, so one or the other.
In static scoping, like our usual Scala land, what is printing?
So if we think about it, we got bar.
We print bar, and then we have bar.
So bar will define its own x, which is an int instead of 30.
And then it will print x.
So it should print bar 30.
What about z?
So z should print z and then its own x and then call bar.
So we should get 30 because it will print it.
And then it will also print it.
and we'll print 30 and then it will print 40, right?
And then, oh, and then we're printing 10.
You know what, I'm missing the detail
that we're printing that.
So let's go back and do that again.
All right, so what do we have?
We got
bar,
And now, we invoke var.
So inside var, so we're in main, I'm going to draw it like this.
We're in main.
I'm going to call it main.
And inside main, we don't really have,
all we have in main is this x that's in int.
By virtue of this line of code up here, we have that, right?
So this is going to be, going to have 10.
Alright, so that's our x.
So then, inside bar, we have a new.
Oh.
Writing the wrong thing.
I'm thinking bar.
We have an X.
And here, oh, you know what?
No, we don't have an X.
I'm going to move this one because this is more like this isn't really a main program,
this is like if you're in the REPL, this is like global scope. I'm just going to call
it REPL because you're out there. You have x here and that's 10. And now inside BAR because
we're using lexical static scoping. Oh I looked in the wrong place look at that
fool has x equals 20 all right but that's okay we're in bar we have a new x so
that is true we've new x right and that's because of this and now we're
gonna set that equal to 30. I should make my stack
So x equals 30.
And then I call foo.
And foo is going to change x to be 20.
And the x it's going to refer to, static scoping, it's going to refer to the one in the closing block.
So that x will now change to 20.
Okay.
And then we'll print x.
Oh, sorry.
Then foo exits.
So we didn't actually have anything on the stack for foo.
Like we had a frame, but we didn't.
So that thing exits, and then we print x, so inside here our x is still 30.
This is our output by the way.
Over there.
So we have 30.
And then, bar exits, right?
I'm not missing anything.
Bar exits.
And then we print x and this time we're going to print 20.
I'm going to just put that up because we'll go through it and we'll do it.
But 30 20, so static scope 30 20.
Now let's do z, so the next line of code would be the z.
So now we're going to create a new stack frame and
this time we're in z.
And then I go into z, I get a new var x 40.
And then I'm going to call it var.
Go ahead.
I'm a bit confused about the static scope one
static scope one because var x int equals 10... when you do bar oh does it change that like var x
to 20? like no. Calls foo. Well because it calls foo and it's static scope when it calls foo,
So let me go back to the previous slide because it's really small.
When it calls foo at line 7, now I'm in foo and I have x, and x is free.
So by static scoping rules, I get it from the enclosing block.
So it references that one.
Var x int equals 10 or var x int equals 30?
Well, it's this var x that was 10.
Ok, and now it's 20?
Yes, let me do it again.
I'll do it again.
So we're in the REPL and we have in global scope, we have x int equals 10.
So that's here, right?
Yes.
so far. Okay, now we print bar. So we're going to print bar, colon, and now we invoke bar.
So when we invoke bar we get a stack frame. And inside bar, line six, the first thing
I do is I have var x, right? So now I have a new x that I'm declaring because of the
word var.
I've got a trip over my chair.
Var x is also an int, and it gets 20.
So, so far you follow that?
Sorry, I said 20, and I meant 30.
30, no.
I'm sorry, I hope I didn't confuse you further.
I'm looking at the wrong line.
So, var x gets 30.
Everybody follow?
Cindy, was that you?
Yeah.
Follow that.
Good.
So then, the next thing at line seven, we call foo.
And when we call foo, we go in there and notice that X is just free there, right?
There's no definition of X within that function or that method, right?
So when we're doing static scoping, we get the meaning for X from the enclosing block of code,
not the calling code, not wherever we came from in the call stack,
but we get the meeting for x in the enclosing block.
So that means that the one that we're changing is this one over here in global scope.
Does that make sense?
Yes.
Okay.
So when we do that, then once that's done, then foo exits.
So we lose the stack frame there.
It goes away.
and then we end up back here in bar
and next line is eight and we print x.
So when we print x,
the x that we're referring to in bar
is the one that has the value of 30.
So, did I forget to print?
No, this I'm printing 30.
This is my first print right after the word bar.
30.
And then I print the value of x
Oh, sorry. I jumped ahead.
So I printed this x here, and then my bar function exits.
So I jumped too far too fast.
See, I think about it and I don't even say it aloud.
So then I get back out to line 14 and I have that print line statement.
And here I print 24, because that's the x that I have in static scope,
is the one that's in scope here.
So that should give us 30 and 20.
But we're not done yet because we have to print z and call z.
So let's see.
If I print the word z, that's that one, and then I invoke z.
New stack frame.
When I invoke Z,
I'm here,
and I have my very own new x,
which is an int.
And this time, I set that x,
this separate x,
equal to 40.
Okay?
And then what happens?
I immediately invoke bar.
So now, I build another sac frame.
and inside bar, oh, look at that.
I have another X, which is an int, and it gets 30.
Is that right?
Yeah, 30.
30, okay.
And then I call foo.
So here we go, another stat frame, foo.
And inside foo, I'm referring to X again,
and I'm setting it equal to 20.
Now, this is static scope.
So the same rule applies as before, right?
It's not going back through the stack frames.
It's going to whatever is the x that's defined that I can just lexically, statically.
The x is this one.
So this time, technically, I actually overwrite the 20 with another 20.
And then foo exits.
And then I'm back in bar.
and I print my 30.
And then bar exits and then I'm back in Z.
And I print my 40 because that's the x I have here.
And then z exits.
I'm still...
I have a print line, and here I'm printing 20.
So I think I get 30, 40, 20.
Is that what I had?
Yeah, that's what I thought.
And then finally,
I call...
Sorry, I print foo.
Hold on.
I call foo.
So when I call foo, I get a stat frame.
And then in there, I am going to update x to be 20, and x is free.
So which x do I update?
Same one I've been updating whenever I'm in foo.
It's always going to be the same one.
With static scope, it's always the same one.
You can read the code and know what it is.
So that's going to change up to zero, not two hundred, sorry, twenty.
All right.
And then, that exits, that foo exits and then I print twenty.
Foo doesn't do any printing, so I just get twenty.
Okay, thank you so much, now I understand.
Sure.
Yeah, it helps to do these, to draw these stack frames out if you're not sure.
So that's how it works for static scope.
So let's talk about the answers for dynamic scope.
Sorry, the coffee is drying me out, so it's hard to talk.
Alright, so for, let's start again.
And this time we're doing static scope.
Now, I'm sorry, dynamic scope.
Now remember, Scala always does static scope, but you might be asked the hypothetical question.
What if Scala, what if this syntax, the language for this syntax, what if it did dynamic scope?
So, obviously we start off by printing bar and then we invoke bar.
I hope that's not too small.
Is that too small?
I can go back.
Okay.
So I invoke bar.
So when I invoke var, I get, oh, before I invoke var, though,
let's, before we get there, we should say we have x int.
Oh, and this time I'm going to draw it in here
because it's not really global scope anymore.
So that there's my var x that's in my REPL.
so then I invoke bar. I get a new X
and I set it equal to 30.
And then I print... oh no I vote foo. I don't even print yet.
I invoke foo.
And inside foo I have to update X to be 20.
Now, because it's dynamic scope, where do I get my x meaning from?
I don't have it defined here.
So I get it from the stack frame from the caller.
Actually, even if it wasn't bar, I would go to the previous stack frame.
I might have other, I mean, in another program,
I might have different stack frames.
But I would have to go back until I found an x.
So here, I find the x here.
So I'm going to update that to be 20.
And then foo's going to exit.
Then I'm going to print line X.
So within bar, I'm printing X.
Oh, it's not print line, it's print.
So I'm going to print 20 because that's the X that's here.
And then X is, I'm sorry, bar is going to exit.
And then I go to the next line of code and print, oh sorry, I go to the end of that line
of code.
Now I print line x, and the x is going to be 10.
That's the only x that could be.
So that should match what we have there.
So 20, 10.
Notice it's different than statics.
OK.
Now we're gonna do Z.
Oh no, I'm jumping ahead.
Sorry.
Oh, no, it is Z.
My brain is like...
Right.
I think Z is the end of the alphabet, so that's the last one.
That's what just happened.
So Z, I go into Z.
So when I do that, I get a new stack frame, see, and I get a new x, and that's going to
be, get the value 40, and then I'm going to immediately call bar.
So I'm back in bar, and back in bar, the first thing that happens is I
declare a new x and it gets 30.
Okay, and then I immediately call foo.
And then inside foo, I'm gonna update
my free variable x to have 20,
and this time it's going to go back
through the stack frames until it finds an x.
If it had one here, it would use it.
If not, it would go to the previous stack frame,
and it would keep going until it finds one.
And so it'll get 40.
That's 20.
Is it 20?
Yeah.
Oh, sorry.
My brain is...
Yep.
Thank you, Dylan.
You're on the ball at eight o'clock at night.
Nine o'clock at night.
So X is 20.
Okay, cool.
And then foo exits.
And then we print the X that we have here.
So that's going to give us 20.
and then we exit bar, right?
So that stack frame goes away.
And then we're back in Z.
And in Z, we're going to then print X.
So the X we have here is 40.
And then that will exit.
and then we're back out here and we will print the X that we have available here and that's
gonna be different. This is crazy behavior. It's crazy what? This is crazy behavior. Yeah well so
it's really actually very simple. All you do is in dynamic scope is you go back through the call
stack, when you can't find something, you don't go out to the global scope.
Right?
Well, and that's not even, remember that with static scope, it's also called lexical
scope.
So you can tell by reading it, if I can't find an X here, I look in the enclosing block
of code.
I look in the enclosing block of source code, static scope.
The compiler can figure it out.
If you think about it this way, with dynamic scope,
the compiler doesn't know what the call stack's
going to look like at runtime, because the compiler
is compiling the code and producing something
that's executable.
So that's why dynamic scope, whenever
you hear the word dynamic, it's runtime.
Runtime, dynamic.
Dynamic runtime.
That's an easy heuristic to remember that.
So it is crazy to think about,
but if you remember these two simple facts,
like DynamicScope, you go through the call stack,
and that's because it's happening at runtime.
And it's determined at runtime.
All right, so we weren't done yet.
We still have, we had the last one, 10,
and then the last thing is we print the word foo,
and then we invoke foo,
and when we invoke foo we go up here we get a new stack frame called foo for foo
and we're going to update x to be 20 and now in this case which x are we changing
go back through the call stack we find the one in the ripple in the outer post
So this would be...oh, I'm usually...and then fu exits.
Then we print the value of x so we should get...I forgot my...so that, 2010, 20, 40,
10, 20.
All right.
All right. So we still did not cover about half of these. So I will probably, I don't
know, I'll come up with something.
But we're at the end of the night. It's three minutes to nine so we're going to
stop there. I might, if I have some time, I'm not, I'm worried about my schedule
because I'm very busy the rest of the week, I just got a message from professor
Riley, he wants to talk to me on Thursday and I was like oh I'm gonna make time for
that because you know. So not because anything wrong, he just he wants to
introduce me to someone. But so what we have due is the study guide is due
Monday night next week we also have this the extra credit is due Friday okay I
encourage you to look through the rest of those slides on me on that last set
of slides I'll try to record a video the cover like I encourage you to look
through those slides and call out questions in discord if you're struggling
or not sure of something.
And we can all chip in
and help each other.
So I'm not always going to be
glued to my computer.
They've recently also made it,
for email,
it's a little bit hard.
I can't get it on my phone anymore.
They changed some security setting
and I would have to give away
permission to wipe my phone
and I won't let them
have that permission.
So I can't get my email.
I complained.
I'm like,
my students want to email me
and I'm not at all.
Like,
I may not see it for the weekend
if I'm away.
So yeah,
Yeah, so work through the rest of these slides.
I will try to record a video, and hopefully that will help.
So any questions?
See you all next week for the exam, or take it remotely.
It's been great teaching you this quarter.
I love talking about this stuff.
Not really a JavaScript, but I love talking about the static type language,
and C since it was my first .
So thanks a lot, and good luck.
And let me know if I can help.
I had the same issue with my email.
I had an on-look on my phone.
Well, I did that and it told me that I needed to allow it to be an administrator of work.
Good night. Take care. Thank you.
Jaden, are you still there?
yes i was just gonna let you know thank you um we won't need you next week because it's finals
um all right i appreciate all your help thank you so much you too all right have a good one
you too bye
bye
good
I don't know what that is going to be like.
I think it's really cool.
It's really cool.
I love this.
take care thank you
that's a wrap
no it's just exams
yeah
scary
good
After only getting three wrong in the midterm, I don't see if I double that for the final,
I'll still pass, so.
I'm hoping you will do well.
Same.
I hope I would have another class with him.
It seems like this is all really teacher-sighted data structures.
Yeah.
So yeah, I started out with data structures.
I think they give all the new folks data structures.
Data structures is the course that is.
What I always say is that's the course where it gets real.
I had fun programming in Python, but now I have to think about all these things.
People have a real hard time making it, actually.
The other problem with data structures at the ball is we teach it in Java, but people
don't get any real Java experience, especially undergrads.
Graduates usually do have some Java experience just because they're out in the field often
and stuff.
But yeah, no, they people really struggle.
So I actually reorganized my data structures course
to do introduction to Java and arrays and for loops
and just how Java works.
Like the first half.
So for up to the midterm, it's just Java.
It's Java and arrays and for loops, and that's it.
And then we don't get into the core data structures material
of data structure one until I think five or six.
I can't remember.
And that's when I start covering stacks and key loops.
That's a nice way of doing it.
Yeah, it helped my undergrads last time.
Yeah.
So what they did was they gave me
data structures one and two.
For two, I only had grads.
For one, I had undergrads and grads.
And they've hired some new folks,
and so they've given them new structures.
But they've also...
This isn't everybody's area of enjoyment, right?
Or expertise, right?
Yeah, exactly.
Because I'm a Scala developer and because I love languages and I think about languages,
I've worked as a programmer for a long time.
And so I've seen different languages and the way things have evolved and stuff.
It sort of is a natural fit for me to teach, because this is really my area of focus.
So I did ask this time around, I was like, I'd be willing to teach data structures.
And they were like, I put in my preferences before fall, and they gave me 447 again.
Because, like, they wanted to, you know, they want to teach other things or whatever.
So, and that's fine.
Like, I love this stuff.
Like, I really love this stuff.
And I know Scalo.
And you're not going to get very many adjuncts who are Scalo.
Yeah, exactly.
I never even heard her language until I took this class.
Yeah.
Which is a shame.
It's a really nice language.
It's a great language.
Unfortunately in the field it's starting to become, it was always niche but it's more niche.
There aren't a lot of scholars. There were for like a good eight, nine, years, ten years.
I've only seen one when I was looking on the Indeed and Handshake.
The other ones are all it's either Java, Python...
I think that's all I'm going to do a little bit of a problem.
You see C once in a while.
C++?
Yeah.
Yep.
Well, and I wouldn't really apply for a C or C++ job,
because I've been pleasantly surprised teaching this class
how much C and C++ I've remembered.
The thing is, I haven't done large scale systems either.
I've done large scale systems with Java and Scala,
and now I'm doing REST.
I'm building a web service to do something.
Yeah.
Sounds fun.
It is fun, actually.
It's fun telling Claude when I'm getting a design.
Because I apply the same design principles.
Like, you know, it's like, well, it's a different language.
But I'm going to structure my code in a similar way.
Yeah, exactly.
Anyway, well, Dylan, good to see you.
Yep, you too.
I'll see you next week.
Nope.
Are you in class for the final?
Or are you?
Yeah, yeah.
Did you register?
No, you have to register.
Yeah, you do.
I only have seven slots because I have 10 people
who are here plus 7.
So you have to register for them.
I thought being an in-person student.
No, you're one of the 10.
So you're in 901.
Yeah.
Yeah, you're fine.
That's what I thought.
I keep thinking, usually the 901, the reason they don't,
the reason they have the two sections
is because there are so many international students,
and they have rules about they need to attend class
in-person for their visa.
I forget that you did this by...
I'll let you know if you have any questions.
Yeah, will do.
You too!
Thank you.
Here we go.
So, let's cut this out.
Thank you.
All right.